A loan worth more than a
billion dollars
linked to Guggenheim
Investments is trading at
about 73 cents
on the dollar—a price that
usually indicates
serious
financial difficulties.
The borrower did not
miss any
payments.
The loan doesn't mature until
2031,
but lenders are
suddenly asking a
much more serious
question.  What exactly is
going on
inside
Mark
Walter's financial empire?  So, Walter
is the billionaire
behind Guggenheim Partners
and TWG Global.  His businesses
span
asset management,
insurance,
private
lending,
real estate, and, of course,
professional sports,
such as the Los Angeles
Dodgers and, until recently
, the Los Angeles
Lakers.  But
earlier this year,
two insurance
companies
controlled by TWG
admitted that more than 20
billion in investments
should have been marked
as affiliated but
were not.  And we will explain
what this means and why
it is so important.  These
disclosures
came after
federal subpoenas that
looked into
loans flowing
from
insurers controlled by Walter
to other parts of his
business empire.
No criminal charges have
been reported, and
the companies deny
that anyone was harmed,
but the accounting
correction is
real.  Federal
investigations
are also very real.  And
now the market is
pricing
financial distress
into some of
Guggenheim's debt.
So, could the
insurance scandal
surrounding Mark
Walter and Guggenheim
expose the entire
private
lending scheme?
Perhaps investors will
finally be able to
figure out the level
of risk and how many
such deals were
hidden in the insurance companies' "
cash machine"
that fueled the
private
lending boom.  And
what it ultimately
led to—things that
will simply
shock you.  Before we
get to the scandal,
we need to find out
who these companies are, what
they do, and how
they are all connected,
as much as possible.
Because Guggenheim is not
one public
corporation with a single
balance sheet.  This is part of a
private network of
companies, financial
structures, and
investments
linked to a man
named Mark Walter.
Walter is
the co-founder of
Guggenheim Partners and its
executive
director.  And Guggenheim
Partners is a
financial services organization
known primarily for
asset management
and investment
banking.  Imagine
BlackRock, because Guggenheim is
their competitor.    The
asset management division is Guggenheim
Investments.  This business
manages the money of
institutions and other
clients, investing
it in government
bonds,
structured
loans, private
investments and
alternative assets
.
Simply put, clients give
Guggenheim money to
manage, and Guggenheim
receives
consulting commissions and
performance fees.  Then there is TWG
Global.  TWG is a holding
company
controlled by Walter,
whose interests
extend beyond
Guggenheim's traditional
asset management operations.  Its network
spans finance,
insurance,
real estate, major
sports investments
like the Los Angeles
Dodgers, and, as we
will see, the Los
Angeles Lakers.
Among the
companies controlled by TWG are two
life insurers that
play a key
role in this story:
Delaware Life Insurance Company and
Clear Spring Life and Annuity Company.
These insurers, like
many others,
collect funds from
policyholders
through products such
as life insurance
and annuities.  They
invest this money
to meet
future
obligations, including
promises of
retirement benefits to
annuity customers.    A
simplified diagram
looks something like
this.  These companies are not
interchangeable, and
one is not
automatically
liable for the
obligations of the other,
but they are linked
through Walter's ownership,
control, and extensive
business network
.  Investigators
are looking into whether
funds from
TWG-controlled
insurers were funneled through
loans and investments
into other
Walter businesses without
proper disclosure of
these connections.  This is
the connection at the heart
of the scandal, but it's just the
tip of the iceberg.
One part of the empire
manages capital, another
collects long-term
funds from
policyholders, and
companies associated with Walter can
receive
financing from the
same network.
It is important to understand what is
really happening here.  Walter
uses
insurance companies
to gain
leverage for
himself and his network,
purchasing assets that he
ultimately
uses himself,
while the debts and
risks fall
mostly on the
insurance business.  That's
what the term
"affiliates" means here.
Walter owns
sports
teams because
Americans
paid insurance
premiums without knowing
where or why
their
money was being invested.  This is the
real
scandal.  In many
ways, this should have been a
separate story.  And
if more people
understood what that
really means,
I think there would be a lot
more attention and
righteous anger
about what's going on.
But let's
untangle this
story, starting with the
most prominent
market signal.
When Guggenheim Structures
issued a
first-tier loan of
$1.18 billion
due in
2031, the debt was
valued back in
November 2024.  By
August 2026, its
value had fallen
to around 72.5–73
cents per dollar.  This is no
ordinary fluctuation.
Trading below 80
cents is usually
seen as a
sign of financial
difficulty, even
if the borrower has
not yet missed payments.    The
decline accelerated
after Guggenheim
Investments reported that
second-
quarter revenue fell 38%
year-over-
year and
profit plunged
77%.  Guggenheim
told
lenders that the significant
drop was
caused by a delay in
recognizing
management fees at Guggenheim
Private Investments.  But this
explanation gave rise to
new fears.
Reporting at Guggenheim
Private Investments reportedly
became the subject of a
whistleblower complaint, which
helped trigger a
broader investigation into
Walter's entire financial network.  So,
management called
a call to
reassure
creditors, lending
briefly
recovered, then
fell to a new
low.
Guggenheim later said that
affiliates
could
buy back some of the
impaired debt,
which could support
the price of the loan, but it
also raises
questions
about the whole
story.  When
affiliates
own,
finance, and
potentially
support each
other, where does
one company's risk end and
another's risk begin?  And what exactly are they
trying
to hide from attention
and from the public?
By the way, these are the kinds of
discussions and truly
detailed analysis we
conduct in our
live format at Euro
Dollar University Live.  The second
Euro Dollar University Live event
will take place in October:
9th, 10th, 11th, and 12th.  We
will be here again in
West Palm Beach.
Join me,
special guests
like Hugh Hendry and
George Hammon, our
regular crew,
plus we plan
to invite a few more
special guests
who may also
join us.
It's hard to overestimate how
much you can
learn by
talking to other
people just like you
, who are in
similar or perhaps
different situations.  Plus
, you know, when
experts with all
their knowledge
are gathered in one
place, in an intimate
setting with a
small group of
people, discussing the
most important topics of
the day—all designed
so that you can
gain information
and insights that you might
never
have otherwise, so that
you can adapt
it in your own way, for
your own purposes, and
make confident
decisions.  As I
said, join
me on October 9, 10, 11, and 12
.  The description contains a
link with all the
necessary
information.  And this
takes on another
very important
significance when you
realize that
insurance companies' money
is at the center of
everything.  As I
said before,
insurance companies
have become leverage
in many of these
questionable deals.    The
life insurer
receives money
today in exchange for
promises that
stretch years
or decades into the
future.
Traditionally,
insurers
have invested premiums in
government
securities,
mortgages, and
highly rated
corporate
bonds.
Reliability was the priority.  The assets were to
remain
available when
policyholders
died, policies were terminated,
or
annuity owners began
receiving pension
payments.  But years of
low interest
rates have made this
model less
profitable.
Private
equity
firms and
alternative
asset managers saw an
opportunity in
acquiring and
partnering with
insurers.  They
gained access to a
huge pool of
long-term
capital that was
no longer available when
regulated banks
began to retreat
after 2008.  So
instead of
relying entirely
on investment
funds, whose clients
might withdraw their funds
during a downturn, the
asset manager
could issue
private loans and
place them in the
portfolios of insurance
companies, which were
backed by fairly
stable
annuity premiums
.  For insurers,
private
lending promised
higher returns with
limited apparent
volatility.  But
volatility is not the
same as limited
risk.  A private
loan does not become
safer because
it is valued
every quarter by
models, rather than
being traded
every second.  And if
the insurer,
asset manager, and
borrower are
linked
through affiliated
structures, valuation
becomes a problem, but
that's only part of the
problem.  An insurer
may actually
finance the same
business network that is
responsible for
managing the
insurer itself.  This is where
conflicts and the risk of
infection come into the conversation.  The most
explosive element of
this
Walter story is not
that these assets
suddenly appeared, but
that they were there
all along and were forced
to be reclassified,
which means
they
were not
properly classified from the beginning.
At least, that's the
claim.  And
the classification
only changed after
regulators intervened.  Delaware Life
and Clear Spring admitted that
more than $20 billion in
loans and investments
on their balance sheets
should have been
classified as
affiliated but
were not.  In general,
insurance companies
are allowed to
invest in
affiliated
entities, but these
relationships must
be disclosed
because affiliated
transactions contain an
obvious conflict
that becomes increasingly
apparent the deeper
you delve into the
story.  The owner of
the insurer could
use
the policyholders' money to
finance
projects that were beneficial to
the owner,
shifting the risks
to the insurance company.
Remember this.
Billions of dollars
presented as
independent investments
were later found
to be linked to
Walter's broader organization
.  In other words,
the premiums that
policyholders
paid to insurance
companies
were funneled into
Walter's wider network,
without the knowledge of the
policyholders or
other investors.
As far as anyone knew,
insurance companies
were doing what they were supposed to:
investing in stocks
or government
bonds, not
making payments to
LeBron James in
exchange for a share of
his future
earnings, or so that
Mark Walter could become
the manager of the LA Lakers and LA
Dodgers.  You can already see how
this can
turn into a
huge problem.
Now TWG claims
it was an
accounting and disclosure issue
, a
dispute, not
fraud, and that there are no
victims,
at least that's the
argument they're
making.  And in the end,
this may
turn out to be true.  At
this stage, we do
n't know for sure.
No criminal charges
have been reported, and
the investigations may
conclude without
any enforcement
action.  However,
the recalculation revealed
a concentration of
affiliated risks
that
insurers,
rating agencies,
and, of course,
regulators were previously
unaware of because they could not
see them, although they had the
right to know about it.  And this is where
this scandal
connects to the
broader
private
lending saga that
we have been following for a year.    In
other words, all of
these things are connected
within the same
ecosystem.  So what
we learn about
Walter's history and the
results of the
investigation could
very well be about
much more, and
you can see how it would have to be
about more than just
Mark Walter's financial affairs.
Private
lending
developed in part
because it seemed more
stable than
public lending.  Public
bonds are traded
daily.  If the market
starts to worry
about a company,
the value of its
bonds can
drop instantly.
Private loans are
typically valued
using models,
comparable
transactions where
available, and
ratings from managers
or third-party
valuation firms.  This
creates an impression of
calm in private
portfolios even
as public markets
deteriorate.  However,
accounting
stability can
hide
economic
instability and
mask risks.    The
public
business development companies (BDCs)
we track
provide one of the
few windows into
this market, and their
shares often
trade well
below their stated
net
asset value when
investors
question the
valuations, dividends
or borrowers in
these portfolios.
Non-trading private
credit funds
are showing a similar
loss of confidence due to
redemption requests
, which we
know have
increased sharply this year.  This
exposes a
contradiction
within
semi-liquid
private
lending.
Investors
are offered
periodic access
to money invested
in assets that
may take years to sell.
Insurance money
helped the industry
avoid this
problem because
annuity capital
was considered
long-term and
stable.  The money
just kept
coming in big
streams.  But if
regulators force
insurers to expose
the truth, and
investors eventually start
to reject all this
nonsense,
reducing private
and affiliated
risks, the
private
lending industry could
lose a source of
capital that
was considered too
permanent to
disappear.  In many
ways, we are
starting to see
signs of this in
Mark Walter's financial empire,
as the empire
tries to find
sources of funds to
try to fix
what is now becoming
public
information.
Delaware Life and
Clear Spring have developed
plans to
reduce
affiliate loans
that are under
scrutiny.  As
Bloomberg recently reported, these steps could
reduce risks by
about six and a
half billion
dollars.  Where will
these six and a
half
billion dollars come from?  Well
, I'll talk about that in a
moment.  S&P
affirmed
Delaware Life's financial strength rating at "A-"
but changed the outlook
from stable to
negative due to
disclosures
, the remediation process,
and the risk
that it could become a
problem.  At the same time,
Mr. Walter himself is changing the
structure of other
parts of his fortune.
He agreed
to sell the Los
Angeles Lakers to
Josh Kushner and Bob
Iger in a deal
that valued the franchise
at a record
$12.5 billion.
Well done.  This comes
less than a year
after he
took control of an
NBA team, which is already
causing some
concerns.
Walter was also reportedly
considering
selling his stake
in Chelsea.  Selling
an asset at a record
valuation
is not in itself evidence of
financial problems.
Owners sell
businesses and investments
for a variety of reasons, but not for
you.  Timing in
this situation
cannot be ignored
.  Walter's network
is trying to
free up capital and
reduce debts to
insurers, while
investigators and regulators
examine how policyholder funds
are moved around the
organizations to
support all these
unconventional deals
and assets.  This makes
every sale
part of the market
calculations.  Is this
normal
portfolio management or a
forced deleveraging campaign
?    The
Guggenheim loan, which
is trading at about
73 cents, which I
mentioned earlier,
suggests that
lenders don't quite
believe in the convenient
explanation for what's
happening.    The
systemic threat to
private
lending and the
broader credit
cycle is not
just about this loan or
even Mark Walter
and Guggenheim.  This is
a repetition of behavior
we have seen
too many times before.
Another
confirmation of
speculative, overly
speculative
activity.  A company
owned by a
private
equity firm
borrows money from a
loan fund.
The fund can then
borrow through a
subscription credit line or an
asset valuation mechanism.  The warehouse
funds the loans
before they
are placed in a CLO.  The bank
provides an additional
loan for a
special project
company.  The insurer
purchases the received
securities or guarantees
their priority
portion.  Insurers
and other entities
can also
use repos
to borrow against
high-quality
assets, which are
contained in everything
I just
listed.  In this
way, they
finance their
high-yielding assets
.  And each of these
individual levels may
look reasonable
in isolation, but together
they create
leverage
spread across
many
organizations and
jurisdictions, which is
often the
main goal.  In
good times, such a
structure increases
profitability and
appears to spread
risks.  During times of
stress, it begins
to appear increasingly
concentrated, where
connected relationships,
instead of
being independent and
reliable, become
increasingly redundant.    A
deterioration in
the borrower's condition
weakens the loan.  This
hurts the fund that
holds it.  Redemptions
or
collateral demands then
put pressure on the fund.
Banks providing
financing
require additional
guarantees.
Structured
securities are expected
to be downgraded.  And
insurers may
be required
to hold more
capital for assets
previously considered
investment-grade.  When
you think of these as
individual entities, it
seems like the base is
broader and can
withstand a downturn.  When
you realize that
many of them are
connected, the base is
much narrower, and the
bulky structure is
more likely to wobble,
if not fall over altogether.
Different regulators
control different
links in this chain.
Banks are subject to
federal supervision
, securities instruments
operate under a
different system, and
insurance
is regulated
primarily at the
state level.  No one authority
has a complete map in
real time.    The
Walter case is important
because it shows that
even a basic map of
affiliated individuals
could be, let's say
, incomplete.  But what
exactly are
regulators looking for?  All we know for now is
that
subpoenas were issued a few months ago,
forcing insurance
companies and other
institutions to rush
to provide belated
explanations.
Federal prosecutors have reportedly
issued
grand jury subpoenas for
Delaware Life and Clear Spring.    The
Securities and Exchange Commission is also
investigating,
at least according to
Bloomberg.  Again, I
would like to point out that an
investigation is not
proof of guilt.
No criminal charges have
been filed, and TWG, as
always, strongly
denies
allegations of
fraud.  But the
investigative process
brings private
information to the
public.  If the
Walter investigation creates a new
template for vetting
affiliate
private
lending deals,
regulators could
apply it
across the board.  The question
will no longer be whether
these specific companies broke the law
, but
how many other
insurance groups
use
similar structures with
similar
economic
risks.  We will shed
light on Walter to
understand how the entire
industry acted,
behaved, and
worked for a long
time.  But it's really
worth understanding why
insurance companies are
so important in this
story.  They are the
basis of all this
cash flow.  These are
firms with high
ratings and
impeccable
reputations that
open the door to
all this
raised capital.
They play a
key role in
transforming
private assets into
investment-grade securities
.  They give it a
cover, a gloss, an
air of
legitimacy.
There is a
certain cyclicality in this approach.
Insurance support
helps
transform
private assets into
investment-grade securities
.  These securities
can then be sold to
insurance companies
or funds that they
form with
premiums, and the
leverage through
repos is the
insurance company's debt,
which is then
redirected to
other places, such as Mark Walter's "
trophy" assets
.  And
banks finance these
funds through insurance
companies.  Funds are
simply transferred
from one level to
another,
using the name
and reputation of the
insurance company
to make everything look
easy, safe, and
low-
risk.  So,
private credit
depends on
more than just
borrowers
continuing to
pay interest.
It depends on
ratings,
leverage,
legal
separation,
stable valuation,
and trust.
That's why you put the
insurance company at the
forefront—because
it looks the
most solid and
impressive.  And
the investigation into
Walter challenges
these assumptions
because it
potentially reveals
everything that has been
hidden.  We
begin to see what
lies behind the facade of the
insurance company, and
how they really "
make sausage."  So
could the
Mark
Walter and Guggenheim insurance scandal
really expose the whole
truth about private
lending?  Answer:
potentially yes.  Not
because a single $
1.18 billion loan
can
collapse a
multi-trillion dollar
industry, and not because
investigations have already
proven fraud.
They didn't do it
.  The real danger
lies in the revealed facts.
Over 20 billion in
investments in two
insurers had to be
reclassified as
affiliated.  These
insurers
are already reducing their
presence.    The
rating agency
changed the forecast to
negative.  Walter
is selling big assets,
key trophy
assets.  And creditors
are assessing the debts
associated with Guggenheim as
problematic, despite
management's attempts
to reassure them.  This
sequence
challenges
the idea that
private
lending risk is
isolated,
transparent, and
controllable.
How many more times
will we see the
same pattern?  This is a
question we
must ask.
Big Wall
Street businessmen use the
insurance premiums of
hardworking
Americans to
purchase trophy
assets, profiting
from it,
while shifting all the risks and potential losses to the
insurers for whom
these premiums
were intended
.  So, who
ultimately bears the
losses and is responsible for them
?    The
asset manager,
the insurer, the government
guarantee system,
or the ordinary people who
bought annuities
believing that their
retirement savings were
being invested
conservatively?    The
Guggenheim loan is not a
crisis.  This is a price
signal.  And the revaluation of
affiliated assets
by insurers is not a
collapse.  This is a flashlight
that illuminates the darkness.
What
this
flashlight ultimately illuminates will determine
whether this remains just a
scandal involving one
billionaire or whether it
truly
exposes the mechanism behind the
real
money mechanism of
private
lending—the
money of hard-working
Americans who
deposit their
premiums into insurance
companies,
hoping that they
will act in their best
interests.